so what's that restraint sense restraint
you've been saying you've been saying
recently that it's important for a
layperson even if they really want to
but the most obvious leads the precepts
pieces but it needs to be taking on us
as I think I discuss I need for you to
talk you think you know your value
precepts but then you can obviously keep
refining it value so that's what it no
more the sense restraint you can really
benefit from it because you can precepts
in itself will not make you practice
Adama so you can have absolutely
unbroken preset but also never really
make the effort to think about
motivation behind your actions whether
it's routine desire or greed or a
version but you just adhere to pieces so
it's still better than not keeping them
at all but in itself it won't because if
it was so then the Buddha would have
said all you need to do is be virtuous
and you will you'll become another hand
so Dhamma there is no Dharma without
sila there's no done without the precepts but
there's no done without the precepts but
Dhamma is not the precepts so sense
distraint starts with the precepts but then you
starts with the precepts but then you
can start to sort of train and practice
understanding all of it so it's not just
you don't do certain things that are
rooted in desire you also want to make
the effort while you're not doing those
things written in desire so while you're
restrained you want to make the effort
to understand why is that good why sense
restraint why is nonsense restraint up also and so
why is nonsense restraint up also and so
that's why I mean like the presets are
obvious things you should not go below
but then if you start following the
principle of anything that's rooted in
desire anything that's rooted in
perversion anything that's rooted in
distraction and delusion is unwholesome
then even some things seemingly
wholesome externally are actually and
also because they did they're determined
there's a wholesome not based on the
external perception of it but based on
whether they are rooted in greed it's
about yeah well it's about you
developing the site of the motivation
behind directions and she's always there
and sort of discriminating and like
because I think see this some people
you're likely to take Center straight
too far hmm yeah of course like that's
the natural respond yeah like completely
only restrain downcast look at anything
and say no to everything now that's what
I mean that the starting point is not
saying no to everything the starting
point isn't saying no to obviously
unwholesome things either against five
precepts or you could take it on the
eight precepts against eight precepts if
it's not against those things it's fine
but that doesn't mean you should be
unclear in regard to either you need to
have clarity why is this fine and why
this isn't fine so yes you've taken it
on as an external value of virtue must
be developed I don't know why but I have
to start developing it that's a
necessary first step but then you also
want to understand why it is necessary
in to what extent it's necessary so you
might say some restraint is is taking
that kind of sort of mechanical you know
just just sort of thoughtlessly avoiding
certain actions is taking it into the
realm of understand
think exactly because as you said it's
it's quite normal to just once you think
okay so venturi is necessary virtuous
valuable senses changes variable then
you start restraining against everything
yeah I want to go from no I want to sit
down no I want to stand up no yeah and
then you just want to serve up
completely yeah there's no wisdom there
either not more than if you just say yes
to everything that's why with a said
self-mortification and sensuality are
basically two ends of the same plane
looked up because he was so restrained
he'd kept his eyes downcast
oh so all you need to do three or seven
or something he's looking at ground just
keep looking at the ground
so does that imply if you look elsewhere
that's where the suffering is routed it
doesn't yeah and that's a problem with
of you by then so basically it's
interesting really is about yeah so the
value of precepts now made even more
personal internalized so speaks and I
really recognize the value of knowledge
a value of restraint as opposed to non
value of lack or restraint you start to
recognize why when you avoid it to look
taste smell touch and so on things on
the desire why is that better
he won't be clear overnight it's not
like oh yes that's why it's something
that needs to be sort of trained to sort
of keep reapplying that value until it
becomes clear and so because it is
better but until you know for yourself
why you will be then adhering to your
sila your virtue your sense restrained
as it will be affected to you it'll be
something you do on account of things
you don't do
but either way there is no understanding
in regard to it so that's what we often
talk about motivation
behind the actions that's what
determines like that's always like even
the precepts breaking the precepts is
bad not because it's better than itself but
not because it's better than itself but
it's bad because it's impossible to
break the precepts without the
motivation being rooted in greed
aversion delusion so there's certain
things that if done that can only be
done either by greed aversion or
delusion five pieces not the five pieces
so that's why that's that's always bad
but and that's why even if somebody who
doesn't want to practice Dharma should
live by the Five Precepts because those
things are on the level of animal
behavior has the Buddha described but
now we are talking about somebody who
wants to practice down not just be a
virtuous person and living up living a
life without any pursuit of the Dhamma
values so you want to practice the
Dharma means you need to be more
restrained than just five precepts but
that restraint now will not be written
you know how they're on the sky they
will always tell you that's always wrong
and it's always always good it would be
determined by why you want to do it and
how you feeling yeah so the same thing
we get at example therefore like go you
want to go I don't know to a library to
get some books to read suitors and
externally it's a good thing because
reading suitors is always good but
internally you might be doing it for
completely wrong reasons as in false
pretences as in unwholesome reasons
because you want to go and socialize
hope meet other people there and sort of
be distracted from your solitude and so
on and so externally the same thing is
there but if you do it for if for the
purpose of reading the suitors it's good
if you do it for the purpose of just
wanting company even if he said it so
that it's not good so that's what you
want to develop the ability to discern
that regardless so far this is always
good it's always bad yes but why am i
doing it what is my reason for wanting
to do this what is
my reason for not wanting to do this
because that motivation behind your
actions behind the possible actions is
always there while those actions or
possibilities of those actions are there
so that's how you get to descend the
intention behind the context the mind in
itself regardless of your behavior so to
speak but by that that behavior must
have been purified to some extent
beforehand because you're not gonna see
motivation behind your actions if you
don't even keep the Five Precepts if you
can't keep the five priests it means you
absolutely know no criteria for any
discernment sort of level the ground
with you keeping the precepts of
habitually avoiding certain actions yeah
you have to start like that but then you
want to start looking behind there so
okay I'm avoiding this because the
priest said this should be avoided okay
so now if the priest says that this well
if the priests it doesn't state whether
something else should be avoided or not
do I avoid it or not how do you know
that so you know that by knowing whether
it's rooted in greed aversion delusion
yeah but if you never look for where
things are rooted for your own
motivations rooted you're never gonna
see that so then you're gonna need and
require others to tell you whether you
can do it go ahead ask out John to tell
you and just these random things and and
just get the answer but even then you
won't think for yourself in that manner
you'll never see craving it no so that's
that's that's what sense restraint is
you don't restrain your senses in regard
to everything you restrain your senses
in regard to things that you know are
rooted in desire a version of
distraction that's all so the practical
basis say you live by the Five Precepts
you keep the eight precepts and then
during the day you keep you have to if
you want to practice that correct form
of sensory strain you have to keep a
corner of your eye on your own mind
because you are about to do something
and you want to see before you do it
whether that's rooted in
Ziya or non desire but it's rooted in
ill-will irritation or no noble and non
irritation whether it's rooted in design
for distraction excitement or non
distraction and on excited and it's not
in the things excitement non excitement
desired non it's not in the things it's
in your own reasons behind doing them
I'm committing to those things so then
you restrain when it's rooted in desire
of great degree diversion delusion if
it's not you don't need to restrain and
that's how you get to then develop that
space for practice so to speak because
if you're just saying no to everything
all the time it's just getting
everything so I was I was not movable
not safe and then as the bully himself
done before he was enlightened I stopped
breathing but yet you would kind of
there would be the big kind of the
extreme combination of that same
attitude of no no no no no no first you
were saying yes to everything now saying
no things like the the deer herd similar
dimensions first one needs debate
carelessly gets hope the second one sees
that then shuns all the food altogether
runs on the mountain starves comes back
its carelessly gets hooked again so the
only way to then not be hold by Mara is
to not shun debate but not eat Achilles
diadem how you do that by discerning by
the things you want to see hear smell
taste touch think about are rooted in
greed aversion delusion or non green
because it has to be losing something no
other nobody is rude on yeah well if you
may have to clarify it you'll find out
that it has to be either green on green
either resistance or non resistance
either distraction delusion carelessness
or non destruction on delusion it has to
be one of those six so if it's the three
on the side of unwholesome restraint
that's all you need to do what we do
next nothing just restraint for as long
as that desire is there when desire is
gone you might even be able to do the
same thing then if it's not rooted in
the same job and they taught the Buddha
described like
as for the monks to eat the food you
cannot eat food because you will die so
if you eat food carelessly it will
automatically be rooted in central
reasons if you eat food carefully it
will not it will be rooted in non
central reasons but if you judge things
as good and bad based on their external
appearance that means eating food is
always best eating food is always
sensuality and that sometimes like
basically people who are not really
experienced but kind of got some sense
of Buddhism we then think also
everything is a desire so being a monk
is out of a desire this is a desire
that's craving that's craving that's
great that's great yes and you single
everything is craving is your craving as
well and there is it has to be like that
when you start that's what were the main
claim is built to be abandoned by the
means of craving conceived by the means
of conceit and desire but I mean the
design so yes everything is craving I
want to be free Frank I crave for that
but it's a result of it I learned how to
restrain things that are rooted in greed
aversion delusion and learn how to
simply be mindful of things that are
rooted in on greed not a version on
delusion so you start to develop a
criteria internally for good is good and
bad is bad which is the beginning of so
the body so the bonanno's crystallize
Kassala and aku so as okusawa
and nobody shorter than so the panna
knows that like Patricia mine except
that this is crystal and this is a
kusuha might have here for the rest of
it like the cassava but he doesn't know
qu so exclusively he does not understand
it if he were to do so he would be so
fun so that's the sense restraint again
like whether you're a lay person or a
monk precept but then within that
container with the precepts you want to
start looking at what is the reason
behind this section of that action what
is my reason what am i reason what is my
motivation what are my intentions are
they rooted in desire either rooted in
carelessness and if it's not clear you
make the effort to clarify it and then
you know oh so I don't have to say no to
everything because that's impossible to
sustain like the day I heard the remnant
of a mountain it's impossible to sustain
that sooner or later you will have to return
sooner or later you will have to return
so what if I were to then just say no to
things that are clearly rooted in desire
aversion and delusion and that's pretty
much all you need to do when you mark
with chapatti and she asked the widow
okay little over giving a brief
instruction so I can go on a retreat so
whatever you know is wholesome cultivate
whatever you know is unwholesome
abandoning ship came out had literally
whoever I'm thinking acting speaking is
routine unwholesome restrain yourself if
it's rooted in non unwholesome fine
he will fortify discernment of that
criteria
because the ignorant mind is not
ignorant because of everything it's
ignorant because of things that are
rooted in greed aversion delusion do you
choose to do that you choose to engage
with that you choose to think not
actually in itself yes it's greed
aversion delusion behind the action that
perpetuates greed aversion delusion for
further actions which is all ignorance I
think in various different ways that
like the same necessary basis of
proximate cause hmm for sense restraint
here's mindfulness hmm sometimes like I
said the body in particular
[Music]
well you wouldn't you wouldn't be you
wouldn't even make the slightest effort
toward sense restraint
unless you've acquired some sort of more
general value of y that would be good to
do and if you forget my sense restrain
is good that's when you don't when you
when you lose it and that's already for
mindfulness keeping the context the
purpose behind said mindfulness of the
body well mindfulness is a body within
well mindfulness is a body within
mindful of the right context and so the
senses but again you would not be
mindful of the senses without the value
of sense restraint that you already know
right here
if somebody says but I don't see the
reason why I should be restrained yeah
no man of mindfulness of the body would
result in them wanting restraint yeah
quite the opposite
that's when you get all the tantric
practices and whatnot in here when
people are mindful in the present moment
for the purpose of sensuality and
everything else so the correct
mindfulness of the body already assumes
you have the value of sense restraint so
if you do have the value of sense
restraint all you need to do is not lose
the sight of your situation because if
you do that's when motivation gets real
rooted in greed aversion delusion if you
are aware of the context of the reason
body and its own nature of that
repulsive not not really something
wasn't hearing - you will not possibly
want it and cultivate design towards it
so mindfulness will bring sense
restraint if you have the right view
yeah yeah so the proximate source for
the center strain is mindfulness the
approximate call for mindfulness is the
right view yeah the body involves
recognizing the nature of it the nature
begins with sort of fun yes so until you
do then it's the precepts and yeah keep
trying to develop mindfulness keep
trying to develop sense we keep trying
to understand
because one thing for sure
yes sense restraint and presets will not
automatically result in the right view
but there will be no review without the
sensory strain increases so you have to
have that and then if you get to
understanding you get a reveal
yeah like this there's a situation where
the Buddha describes a sensor to the
wild animals so we stay on the more
vague sense has its own feeding ground
yeah yeah yeah your eyes want science
hospital sick mind wants images in these
images depends it's defined by them
exactly but desire lust a version
delusion none of that was rooted in
either I know the science that's you
trying to well that's used really yeah
yeah that's you well implying the notion
of their mastery but it's really like
you simply wanting pleasure because the
I experience pleasure on account of or
rather the I experience AgrAbility on
account of certain sites and disagree
ability no kind of some other sites none
of those is a problem but for an inner
mind agree ability means lust for
pleasure disagree ability means a virgin
from get rid of it a version too much
pain so you keep them acting toward
sight sound smell taste touch is not
because of I wanting the agreeable
that's kind of implied but because you
want pleasure of that agreeable and you
want that or rather you want to get rid
of that whichever version to vote on
account of disagreeable but if you were
to remove your that motivation of I want
pleasure I don't want pain it's literally
I don't want pain it's literally
agreeable disagreeable that's how the
elements will become bearable even the
like adversity discomfort will not
overwhelm the mind or infect it with
with a version and your will and anger
because that's a completely separate
domain which obviously with ignorance
it's all it's the starting point so to
speak so yes if you're a person can
distinguish the difference between
agreeable and disagreeable and last in a
version you a close step closer to
understand last in a version
so that's the important point thing I
think here is to know things sensory
strain means say no to everything all
the time
why are you going to say no to it or not
we'll be determined whether it's rooted
in desire a version distraction that's
it if it's not
Thanks fine then just be mindful of it
which you will automatically be mindful
because see you're already mindful of
motivation behind what you're about to
do and now you know that their
motivation is not unwholesome so you're
already aware of it and you will remain
aware of it because you keep an eye in
case it becomes an awesome it's
important to you to see what it becomes
unwholesome yes I might go to library to
read the sutras and once I'm in the
library give the suitors then my mind
might change and I'm I want to stay
longer to get to meet other people and
socialize and distract myself and
whatever else
oh you become aware when that changes
now it's a different thing now I'll
leave the library because of that and
that's how again you will become you
eventually you can become your own guide
you will know what is it's careful you
will know what's unlawful no but going
to library is always good everybody says
that all the monks say that all the
people say that all the Buddha said it
well it isn't they cannot possibly know
where your motivations rooted and if
they say that that is always good means
they're not aware of their own
motivation how a factor that determines
whether things are good or bad how
difficult it is to judge yeah yeah well
like in the sutras exactly
oh he speaks so so he speaks roughly and
harshly that's going complain to the
Buddha he must be a complete lunatic he
speaks like that
so what none of that was rooted in hate
or aversion it was just the way he
speaks for whatever reason it's kind of
normal inevitable to start like that but
we're talking about somebody who doesn't
want to practice Dhamma wants to
progress in it as a person or as a monk
doesn't matter you have to start
developing that wellness of motivation behind
that wellness of motivation behind
direction behind your views even behind
the reasons you think this or don't like
that or say this and don't say that you
would see why and that's how you get to
undermine all the wrong views as well
because you stand up question you know
just directions but even what you think
so so you like I think you know
enlightenment in freedom from suffering
is such and such but how do I know that
why do I think that where is that where
those thoughts rooted where is me
investing effort to maintain their view
defended view argue that view when is
their rooted why am i doing that so from
your average sense restrained you came
to the point of restraining the outflows
of your bad views because you actually
started to question them and then you
understand the most of the views will
held simply because they were agreeable
yeah same principle they were Pleasant
these ideas were pleasant agreeable and
that's why I wanted that pleasure to
persist and then the opposing view that
I heard was disagreeable that's why it's
wrong that's why when Chris said no
because I understood discrepancy
contradiction in it a fault went against
no he's simply because it displeases me
Muruga would become more apparent if you
stop practicing basic awareness of
motivation behind your day-to-day
actions doesn't matter how small those
actions are and it's not about I must
figure out why seelix for example or I
want to get up why because this because
it is because it's yeah but why do I
want to get up now you need to wait for
the end of your action to find out why
you want to do it because that's not
where the motivation is force you in
their direction yes so what together why
I did I would I need to drink water yeah
he's that unwholesome really it's a
necessity so I get up oh I'll get up
because I want to go and talk to such
and such ah so then the only purpose
before you actually come here to do it
becomes clear
it's I want to go and engage and
socialize and distract myself so the
purposes it's not last
I'm not last what about that person it's
not anger or not angry but if there is
no other purpose to go and talk to them
why are you doing it because you're
bored so that's an awesome you got your
answer before you want to do it and
figure out and then afterwards oh yes
there was and also you don't want to
wait for that because otherwise you
wouldn't be doing that action in the
first place
if there is already not a motivation for
the present if there's no reason present
the action would be unintelligible so
that's I mean you find it right here
right now before you actually do it
before you say before you think it and
for as long as there is a possibility to
go and talk to such-and-such food for as
long as that is there for the same
amount of time basically the motivation
to do so is there it's not like I missed
a second so I my motivation escaped me
know is there is there a desire to go
and do such a such action still present
yes means their motivation has to be
there because motivation unifies them
unifies the purpose intention so even if
you've not gone and distract yourself by
talking the fact that intentions there
means that desire will be an awesome so
understanding intentioned restraining
intention is rooted in greed aversion
delusion that's how you stop
perpetuating ignorance towards it
and that's what the mindfulness comes
from as well knowing the motivation
behind your contact is that fundamental
context of your situation because you
always must be doing something well
doing any I'm just sitting here which is
what you're doing yeah so why am I doing
this he's a question you can ask yourself not
he's a question you can ask yourself not
for the purpose of finding some ultimate
answer it seems for the purpose of
pretty establishing the context that you
are doing something which is there
whether you see yeah in the same sense I
said there has to be time it has to be
rooted in desire in greed or non-greed a
version of non aversion distraction or
non distraction it has to be in
something so you just want to fire stuff
like I must find something that's not
rooted in anything that's impossible
I must simply replace grid with non
green if it's routine a version I better
replace it with non a version if its
routine distraction I'll replace it with
non distraction that's all you can do
but is this notion of again when I said
there is no clarity then the notion of
single to everything and nothing as a
result of it you then accept everything
in nothing so then you allow this view
of like oh it's this the state you're
after in your practices it's neither
here nor there nor in between the two
but it's really just no whenever they
agreed abandon it whenever there is no
grid cultivated maintain it you know
protect it so it lasts longer don't
distract yourself from it and then you
get up now is it lost to normal oh it's
lost don't cultivate it donate detainee
don't welcome it
be mindful until it goes away don't act
out of it restrain yourself
now it's non bust I don't have lost any
more protected cultivated entertain it
welcome it understand it and so on and
other hardship will have to be the
result of that
so in the beginning everything is
affected by desire say for the layperson
doesn't mean you need to say no to
everything you simply need to see
whether whatever you have a desire to go
and talk to somebody
he said against the five pieces enough
taken off with that talking both I don't
know seducing someone else for lying or
gossiping maybe then I won't do it while
they're talking about no one involved
its saluting desire you cannot not have
that but you want to start rounding it
up and making it less and less and also
then if it's eight precepts so say
you're a celibate or I want to go and
talk to the you know opposite sex that I
might be attracted to what's the purpose
of it there is no any practical purpose
then you would won't do it why because
it can then bring more desire toward
something that can compromise your
precepts so they're not they're not set
in stone when I say they're not set in
stone doesn't mean they're negotiable it
just means they are not set in stone in
in how far you take them in terms of
your restraint and refinement of the
principle not in terms of blind is
saying no to everything and everyone if
it's not rooted in desire okay
then then you can go and do it if it's
all written in greed aversion delusion
sorry so once you stop engaging with
things that are against the presets stop
cultivating things that are clearly
looting greed aversion delusion then
your desire towards agreeable and desire
to is disagreeable will be seen on the
level of the eye ear nose taste and
touch he will not be infected by craving
on the level of the mind which is how
used to be before any agreeable was
lustful any disagreeable was was
basically resisted the words any neutral
was distracted from
so with this ayah you practiced and I
resulted seeing through to desire
no thanks um any costume one just that
each person at practice practice is the
way you just said knowing the motivation
and keeping to the wholesome avoiding
that an awesome it's not gonna
physically look the same no we do the
same thing physically looks the same no
of course not yeah you know everyone who
does that lives in the first not
everyone who does that who is very gross
and those and doing those things because
as I said exactly oh I want to go and
where that grows you live in the forest
wait what's my motivation
oh it's actually I want to be better
than everybody else so that's not
wholesome isn't it that's extremely good
so instead the reason and if that's the
sole reason you you want to do it then
you don't do it oh maybe I kind of am a
bit conceited about it but I also found
out that when I'm in the forest exposed
to elements endurance fatigue insects
and so on my mind gets very sharp okay
so that good that becomes your reason
now to do it but if you never stop and
think about the reasons behind
directions none of this will ever become
intelligible but yes some people will
always going to forests will always be
an awesome they can also not to do it
for unwholesome reasons would you say
yeah and like romantic reasons exactly
romantic reasons are unholy yeah so that
I mean it's determined and when they ask
the Buddha man David odde how's the
Buddha to make all these ascetic
practices mandatory because you know
there's no inspiration
they're good the Buddha said no let
those who want to live in the forest
live in the forest those who don't want
to not in other words let those who know
then living the forest is beneficial for
them leave it to live there and those
who know that it's not beneficial don't
let their which means you need to know
what's beneficial and you will know that
if you become aware of motivation behind
your day-to-day actions which really we
said before that those do Tunga
practices it's being clumped together
hmm the 13 - Tigers I don't know if that in
the 13 - Tigers I don't know if that in
the commentary
but if count that together this is the
do target practice which results in ya
executive run practice determine the
detangle yeah yeah they come yeah
max were reg wearing whatever living in
the forest because that's what was
making their right of you grow but now
you just need to hear - I'll never lay
down and somehow that will result in
magical enlightenment random so
everything to do is with the desire you
want to start doing things that are not
unwholesome out of that desire they
don't will this thing that is routine
desire the Patriot greed perpetuate the
version perpetuate delusion no you want
then you can do that desire because yeah
I want to have a desire to be sense
restrained because I value Dhamma and I
hopefully will ever achieve complete
freedom from suffering
that's a ballot design will their desire
bring more desire more greed aversion no
then do it
oh but I have a desire to go and you
know pick out and socialize and
everything will that bring more greed
aversion yes then you don't do it but
people because they recognize everything
is written desire trying to deny all
desire no there is a desire they will
bring more desire and there is a desire
they will sort of take you away from
greed aversion delusion and you will
know that when you start discerning the
motivation behind directions that's
thing if you when you begin the practice
you find a teacher maybe you think I was
kind of he's talking about and then you
try to emulate him and a physical that's
not good that's not for you that might
be the wrong thing to be doing so you
might be the monk might know what he's
talking about but living in a very
luxurious place and say well the agem my
teacher he lives him in a serious place
so I can I
therefore it's right for me also it's
actually you might have to live more
assertively yeah the Weisse person
ascetic month you might have to not go
so fine yeah well you should be learning
from your agent he's not how he lives in
track time you like that is what it's
the right view yeah it you should be
developing the right criteria listening
and then you will know what's right for
you in that sense because you learned
rightly from that person but that person
that needs to know what they're talking
about yeah so that was like in the suitors
yeah so that was like in the suitors
when the Buddha said when the man said
all these monks respect to Buddhist so
much and says why do you think that they
respect me so because master Gautama
praises heating heats lethal and praises
eating little he lives in the forest and
plays live in the forests and wears red
robes and praises wedding and said no
that's not the case I have disciples
that live on like one handful of rice
every third day and I sometimes get bold
to the brain full of food and sometimes
two bowls to the brim I eat so if they
were to respect an accommodating little
they wouldn't because I don't always he
little sometimes I stay in King's
palaces they with respect you know kind
of sleeping enough they wouldn't because
I don't do that all the time but why do
they respect me because I showed them
the phone over truth I showed him the
right view I shouldn't I shouldn't feel
from suffering you know all these guys
are practicing the more you directly
visible here now and then they realize
lifestyle things you do how it fits with
that understanding or not but if people
can only judge the book by the cover
that's it that's their only criteria so
when they see the Buddha eating a lot
they would dismiss him as his former
friends there but now that's not to say
also I can then eat carelessly as much
as the one well are you so Tappan Ariana
got me if you're not then you better be
careful resting for a lot of people will
start trying to emulate the person a
teacher
in a ways so there is a responsibility
in the teacher as well you know Hindus
yes because that's where people are
gonna come from yeah well that's why it
said like in the sutras when when
somebody like maha kassapa was refused
to leave the forest after the buddha
inviting himself said come and live with
me i get their shelters and lodgings and
nice robes you've done your work so no
no I found all this agreeable this is
not unpleasant for me because you know
he's always honest and then they would
have said well done you're practicing
for the sake of future generations
that's what it means it is inspiring
factual inspiring can be rooted a right
or wrong reasons but it's factually
inspiring for people when they hear
about it so that's what that
responsibility comes it but it's not
really that kind of you responsible for
what you do
you're responsible for what view you put
out there if you're putting out the view
that simply by emulating certain type of
behavior you will arrive at the right
view that's that's what you're
responsible for that's what the Buddha
said there is no such thing not a single
thing in the world as blameworthy as
wrong view and presenting non Dharma as
Dhamma inadvertently doesn't matter as a
result of your views or for to say
practices people now do that thinking
they're practicing while in reality
they're not that's what if sometimes
like you know you do certain things and
people see that and they take that to
mean that well that's not directly on to
you but if you say an encourage review
then emulating behavior will result in
freedom from suffering yeah that's a new
perhaps because you wouldn't be
encouraging it you wouldn't be
encouraging it unless you have that be
like oh like the other the other one who
is the other one we spoke about before
like oh yes so sense restraint is hard
it's difficult to be sense restrained
especially when you live in the lay
world yeah that's that's factually
correct but it's also factually correct
that there is no Dharma without the
sense restraint so in other words you
can then say oh so practicing Dharma in
the label is very hard and that's an
accurate statement but if you say
sensory strange is hard and there's no
done without sensor strange but sense
restraint is
that's why maybe you don't need to do it
and do something else but still
presented on the pretext of practice in
the Dhamma and that's how directly
obscured Adama yes sense restraint is
hard and virtually impossible to develop
for most people which means drama is
then virtually impossible to dwell but
there are those who could develop it but
they won't develop it if you tell them
no no no you don't have to be sense
restrained just because of the vast
majority for which it makes no
difference what you tell them they will
know be sense restraint but because of
that dependent to them you did dilute
the principle necessary principle for
practicing of the Dhamma which is the
sense restraint so you would have been
like what he said before like when the
Buddha decided first he didn't want to
teach because most world would not
understand the Dhamma then he agreed to
teach but this would be if he were to
say oh so I want to teach the Dhamma but
most of the world can't understand the
Dharma because they can't be restrained
so instead of teaching the principle of
restraint in the Dhamma
which is the only thing I can teach let
me teach them something else yeah
because they can't understand this so
let me just make them happy that's
ridiculous if you were to say that
listen I'm not gonna teach you Dhamma
you can't understand it I'll just make
you feel good that's fine you're honest
but if you say well listen Dhamma is
hard but I'm still under the pretext of
teaching you the Dhamma but I'll just
instead make you happy and now you are
happy and you think you're practicing
the Dharma that Arjun told you and
you're not
so yeah it's virtually impossible for
most people but for those who would for
whom it isn't that's what these
principles are for again it's similar
innocent ISM there's a horse they just
the sound of a whip is ready to do the
work there's another horse who needs to
see the word then gets ready to do the
world there's the one that needs to feel
the whip and then there is the full type
which is vast majority of people that
you just flog in the fog and makes no
difference
so then that simply means if sense
restraint is hard means practice of the
dam is hard not like sense restraint is
hard so let me change those terms so I
can still practice the Dharma that's
impossible